Guide to the UE News Records,1936-1997 UE.12
ULS Archives & Special Collections
UE News Records
1936-1997
ULS Archives & Special Collections
United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America
UE.12
18.75 Linear Feet (15 boxes)
The People's Press was the official newspaper of the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America (UE) from 1936 to 1938 and was replaced by the UE News as the official paper in 1939. This record group contains research and correspondence documenting subscription information and articles within both UE newspapers. Digital reproductions of selected images are available online.
History
The United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America (UE) formed as an independent union in 1936 and then was incorporated as the first major addition to the Congress of Industrial Organizations in 1938. The People's Press served as the union's primary publication from 1936 to 1938. The People's Press printed several editions for various organizations around the country with the UER&MW edition standing for United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers. In 1939, just three years after its formation, the UE created the UE News to replace the People's Press as the union's primary publication. The UE News focused on labor history and informing subscribers of current events affecting the working class. Throughout its history the paper covered pertinent topics such as McCarthyism, war, strikes, and other issues pertaining to the labor movement, often reflecting the union's rank and file mentality in that the members make all decisions regarding the UE. In addition to a variety of articles, the paper included editorial and political cartoons by staff cartoonist Fred Wright, who worked for the UE from 1949 until his death in 1984. He has since been succeeded by Gary Huck, who maintains the union's tradition of utilizing humor to illustrate various issues. The UE News serves as an outreach tool used by the union to communicate not only with its members, but with anyone seeking information regarding the union's activities.
Tom Wright was named the first managing editor of the UE News in 1939 and was responsible for establishing the newspaper not only within the union, but the entire labor community. In 1967, Wright retired from the UE News and James Lerner, a reporter and photographer for the paper, became the new managing editor. Under Lerner, the UE News created a close affiliation with the workers in factories, foundries, and offices organized by the UE. Lerner was succeeded by Peter Gilmore as editor of the UE News sometime in the late 1970s. In addition to continuing Lerner's communication with other international labor organizations, Gilmore focused the paper on labor issues in the Soviet Union and Scotland. Alan Hart succeeded Peter Gilmore in 2006 as managing editor of the newspaper. The UE News is still in circulation today, signifying the strength and unity of the union while informing members of issues involving the working class. Issues of the newspaper are printed eight times a year and can now be found online.
Scope and Content Notes
This record group contains research and correspondence regarding the People's Press and UE News. Research includes newsletters and clippings from a variety of sources concerning union locals and companies. There is information regarding plant closings and strikes, particularly in the 1970s. Also present are notes taken at several UE Political Action Conferences, which include information regarding legislation and labor issues in the mid 1990s. The correspondence contains subscription information, as well as letters received by UE News editors concerning articles and photographs published in the paper. Press releases are also present in this record group. Although records in the collection date from 1936 to 1997, there are several gaps within the documentation.
Arrangement
These files are arranged chronologically by topic.
Subgroup 12.1. Plant Closings and Strikes
Subgroup 12.2. Clippings and Convention Notes
Subgroup 12.3. Correspondence
Subgroup 12.4. Mimeograph Plates
Access Restrictions
The records of the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America are closed for a period of twenty-five years after their creation.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America in 1976 and 2004.
Previous Citation
UE News Records, 1936-1997, UE.12, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically at http://images.library.pitt.edu/u/ue/.
Related Material
Fred Wright Papers, 1953-1986, UE.13, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
UE News Photograph Collection, 1933-1998, UE.14.1, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Separated Material
Individual issues of the People's Press and the UE News, both on paper and microfilm, have been cataloged and are housed at the Archives Service Center. Audio cassettes containing news broadcasts regarding labor struggles can be found with other cassettes from labor collections in the audio cabinet.
Newspapers; Periodicals; Labor; Correspondence; Electric industry workers -- Labor unions -- United States -- Periodicals; Press releases; Electric industry workers -- United States -- Periodicals; Gilmore, Peter; Lerner, James; Lewis, Robert Z.; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America
- Plant Closings and Strikes, 12.1.
  Scope and Contents note
  These files contain information on various strikes and plant closings from 1979 through 1996. Records contain information on individual strikes; newsletters and pamphlets authored by the striking locals; information about the negotiations between strikers and the companies; UE reporters' notes on the events; and some clippings of published news stories pertaining to the strike. General Electric (GE) and Westinghouse strikes in New York, California, Florida, and Indiana are among those covered.
  - Westinghouse Electric Negotiations, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Soviet Trade Union Delegation Visits, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - WBCN-FM Radio Strike, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Connecticut Flyers, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Runaway Shops and Plant Closings UE, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - GE Plant Elmira, NY, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 06-07)
  - Steward Warner Strike Local 1154, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - GE Plant Closing Ontario, CA, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 09-12)
  - Paragon Gears Plant Closing, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Plant Closings, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Morse Strike and Plant Closing, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
  - UE-GE Negotiations, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Timex Plant Closing Dundee, Scotland, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dura-Vent Plant Closes, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Litton Co. Microwave Cooking Products, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Litton's United Twist Drill (UTD) Plant, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - GE/Collective Bargaining Committee Negotiations, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Why Bryant Electric Should Stay in Bridgeport" Essay Contests, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 04-05)
  - Closing of Bryant Electric Plant, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - GE plant Closings in Tampa, FL and Decatur, IN, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cox Creek Copper Refinery, UE Local 125 Baltimore, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Circuit-Wise, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Erie Plastics Campaign, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Dynapert Sale, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - UE Local 214 Prince Pasta Organizing, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - University of Iowa Campaign to Organize Graduate Students, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Clippings and Convention Notes, 12.2.
  These records contain clippings from various labor publications and newspapers with a special emphasis on "Legally Speaking," a column in the UE News written by Robert Z. Lewis, and the Shop Paper News Service. "Legally Speaking" discussed the decisions made by arbitrators and the negative legal ramifications they had on the workers. The Shop Paper News Service, another UE publication, was a quick summary of labor stories the national office sent out for individual locals to put in their shop papers. Stories were only a few lines long and covered issues like legal decisions, unemployment rates, and strike updates. This subgroup also contains reporters' notes on conventions and copies of speeches made there.
  - UE News "Legally Speaking", 1963-1982 (Box 3, Folder 01-08)
  - Shop Paper News Service, 1977-1989 (Box 3, Folder 09-16)
  - UE Sample Contract and Guide to Hazards in the Workplace, 1958, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Questionnaire on UE News, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - UE Local 209 Workforce Statistics, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - UE Steward Clippings, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Salvadoran Electrical Workers' Union, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - UE Local 610 – Westinghouse Air Brake Co., 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - John H. Hovis Speech, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Labor Newspapers, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Political Action Anti-Reagan Leaflets, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - UE-GE Conference, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - UE Political Action Conference, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - UE Political Action Conference Washington D.C., 1995 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - UE Political Action Conference Iowa, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - UE Political Action Conference, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Correspondence, 12.3.
  This subgroup contains records of correspondence between the UE News and various other groups and individuals. Several files are devoted to individual subscribers' correspondence, such as requests for change of address or subscription service and claims of faulty paper delivery. There is also communication between various districts from 1938 to 1941 concerning subscription information. The exchange of ideas and mutual admiration between the editor of the UE News, Peter Gilmore, and other labor activists and union publication editors, both overseas and in the United States, is extensively documented in personal letters and news stories from 1977 to 1996. Also included are posters used for organizational meetings and displaying industry statistics.
  - People's Press Subscriptions, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 01-02)
  - District 1, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 03-07)
  - District 2, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 08-13)
  - District 3, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 14-17)
  - District 4, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 18-22)
  - District 5, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 23-27)
  - District 6, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 28-32)
  - District 7, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 33-37)
  - District 8, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 38-42)
  - District 9, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 43-47)
  - District 10, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 48-52)
  - District 11, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 53-57)
  - District 12, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 58-60)
  - Correspondence with Heidi Steffens, 1974-1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Washington D.C. Office, 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Edna Farkas, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 03-04)
  - Requests for Add, Change, or Delete from UE News Mailing List, 1958-1981 (Box 5, Folder 05-07)
  - Correspondence with Washington D.C. Office, 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 08-11)
  - Mailing List Correspondence with Locals, 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
  - Subscription Correspondence, 1980-1986 (Box 5, Folder 15-19)
  - People's Press Subscription Breakdowns, 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - UE News Memos, 1977-1983 (Box 6, Folder 02-04)
  - Letters from Donors, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Publicity Education Correspondence, 1976-1985 (Box 6, Folder 06-08)
  - Peter Gilmore Correspondence, 1977-1996 (Box 6, Folder 09-28)
  - UE News Correspondence, 1938-1986 (Box 7, Folder 01-26)
  - Michael Funke Correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Consumer Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - GE Press Clippings, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1916, 1932, 1989, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - News Clippings regarding Square D, 1948-1954 (Box 8, Folder 05-06)
  - Press Clippings, 1977-1988 (Box 8, Folder 07-10)
  - Officers Tour Clippings, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1989-1996 (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
  - Press Releases, 1988-1995 (Box 8, Folder 14-16)
  - UE News Bulletin (Canada), 1990-1992 (Box 8, Folder 17-23)
  - Film Catalogs (Box 8, Folder 24-28)
  - Posters and Graphs (Box 9)
- Mimeograph Plates, 12.4.
  This subgroup contains mimeograph plates of individual head shots of hundreds of union rank and file members. Pictures portray members of union locals as well as national UE leaders, such as Secretary Treasurer Julius Emspak; Director of Organization James Matles; General Presidents Albert Fitzgerald and James Carey, who later became president of the CIO-IUE; and labor cartoonist Fred Wright. These plates are artifacts of the printing process used by the UE News and were typically used repeatedly by the paper to depict union officials and other important people.
  - Mimeograph Plates (Box 10-15)